Guide to the El Pueblo, Inc. Records, 1994-2020; 1994-ongoing RL.11105
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Administrative, 1992-2020; 1992-ongoing; 5
  - Sponsors A-Z, 1992-2008; 35 folders (Box 13)
    This set of folders documents contracts, agreements, and financing related to sponsors of events organized and held by El Pubelo Inc., especially La Fiesta del Pueblo. Sponsors include corporate, media, and other private entities such as Univision, Telemundo, Que Pasa Media, La Ley Radio, major insurance companies and banks such as Blue Cross Blue Shield of North Carolina, Nationwide, BBandT and Wachovia, and food companies such as McDonalds and Mahatma Rice. Researchers of coporate sponsorship of non profit organizations, non profit organization management, and business history would likely be interested in these documents.
  - Grants A-P, 2000-2006; 68 folders (Box 14)
    This set of folders documents the grant application and management process for El Pueblo Inc. from 2000-2006, arranged alphabetically from A-P. The records contain information on grants from a number of foundations, councils, and trusts, both private and public such as the NC Arts Council, the Carnegie Foundation, the Duke Endowment, the Ford Foundation, the NC Governors Crime Commission, Hispanics in Philanthropy, the Ms Foundation, and most notably the John Rex Endownment.
  - Grants Q-Z, 2000-2006; 38 folders (Box 15)
    Folder marked Vitaminas contains correspondence with then Attorney General of NC Roy Cooper
    This set of folders documents the grant application and management process for El Pueblo Inc. from 2000-2006, arranged alphabetically from Q-Z. The records contain information on grants from a number of foundations, councils, and trusts, both private and public such as the Racial Justice Collaborative, the Susan G. Komen Foundation a primary funder of the Comunidad Sana program, Wake County, and the Z. Smith Reynolds Foundation.
  - Grants A-Z, 2006-2012; 49 folders (Box 16)
    This set of folders documents the grant application and management process for El Pueblo Inc. from 2006-2012, arranged alphabetically from A-Z. The records contain information on grants from a number of foundations, councils, and trusts, both private and public such as the Coalition for Comprehensive Immigration Reform (CCIR), Hispanics in Philanthropy, NC Governor's Crime Commission and other NC State government funds, the Susan G. Komen Foundation, US Department of Education, US Department of Justice, Wake County, and the Z. Smith Reynolds Foundation.
  - Florence M. Siman's administrative Files, 2004-2018; 3,245 files in 145 folders; approximately 2.73 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0001)
    This folder contains a variety of administrative files related to grants, programs, and events adminstered by Florence M. Siman, the Health Program Director and founding Board member of El Pueblo, Inc. It includes applications and reports for major grants from the John Rex Endowment and Susan G. Komen Foundation as well as media files related to campaigns, conferences, and events. There is extensive documentation of the Lideres de Salud and Comunidad Sana programs.
  - Administrative electronic records, 1997-2016; 6,301 files in 1,083 folders; approximately 5.68 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0008)
    Includes the adminstrative files and documentation of the operations of El Pueblo Inc. Contains financial records such as budgets, grant applications, and audit reports as well as extensive files on the operations of the Board of Directors.
  - El Pueblo website, 2014-2020; 2014-ongoing
- Programs, 2001-2016; 6
  The Programs 2001-2016 series covers major programs and campaigns planned and implemented by El Pueblo Inc. The majority of the series focuses on their public safety efforts, in particular the Por Nuestra Seguridad program that sought to curb DWIs and promote the proper use of child car seats among other public safety issues. Included also are extensive records on the collaboration with the Governor's Highway Safety Program, which funded most of the efforts and sponsored the creation of public safety PSAs in both English and Spanish.
  - Promotional materials, 2004 (Box 17)
  - PARE, 2009-2010; 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Public Safety grants, 2009 (Box 17)
  - DWI Project, 2006-2009; 12 folders (Box 17)
  - Collaboration with Governor's Highway Safety Program (GHSP), 2001-2007; 8 folders (Box 17)
  - Collaboration with Governor's Highway Safety Program (GHSP), 2007-2009; 20 folders (Box 18)
  - Collaboration with Governor's Highway Safety Program (GHSP), 2009-2014; 27 folders (Box 19, Box 20)
  - Public Safety electronic records, 2000-2014; 8,437 files in 767 folders; approximately 28.6 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0015, Box 21)
    Materials such as adminstrative and promotional documents related to the Public Safety division of El Pueblo Inc. and the programs run by them. Includes the Nuestra Seguridad program featuring campaigns to curb DWIs and encourage the proper use of child car seats. Features information on grants and collaborations with other non-profit organizations or government entities.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Electronic records in this file have been migrated to the electronic records server and must be used in our reading room. The original media in Box 21 is closed to use.
  - Programs electronic records, 2003-2016; 5,315 files in 466 folders; approximately 7.06 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0011)
    Documents related to ongoing programs and related events. Includes Leamos Juntos, cultural programs, social justice curriculum, and community leadership iniatives.
  - Por Nuestra Seguridad edit master, cued to 3:23 before bars, approximately 40 minutes, Spanish and Spanish with English subtitles, 2004 (Box 21, Video-cassette RL11105-DVCAM-0001)
  - Por Nuestra Seguridad, approximately 40 minutes, Spanish version, Spanish version with English subtitles, circa 2004 (Box 21, Video-cassette RL11105-BCAM-0001)
  - Por Nuestra Seguridad El Pueblo Inc., Versión en espanol, circa 2005 (Box 21, Video-cassette RL11105-VHS-0001)
  - Spanish TV public service announcements, 7 medicial and health related PSAs, 2005 (Box 21, Video-cassette RL11105-VHS-0002)
  - Por Nuestra Seguridad instruction guide for videos, 2005 (Box 17)
  - Brochures child seat safety, 2005 (Box 17)
  - Microcassette on coalition building, circa 2003 (Box 21, Audio-cassette RL11105-MCS-0001)
    Microcassette taped to folder outlining project to build a coalition of Latino serving organizations across NC
  - Microcassette on coalition building, circa 2003 (Box 21, Audio-cassette RL11105-MCS-0002)
    Microcassette taped to folder outlining project to build a coalition of Latino serving organizations across NC, Interview with Jeannette Butterworth of the Center for Participatory Change in Hendersonville, NC
  - Notes on coalition building, circa 2003 (Box 17)
    Detailed notes on a project to build a coalition of non-profits across North Carolina working with the Latin American community and Latino issues. Linked to microcassettes that have interviews and other audio recordings related to the project.
- Youth, 2001-2015; 7
  The Youth 2001-2015 series covers the records of the youth division of El Pueblo Inc. Youth leadership is one of the main facets of the work of El Pueblo Inc. and due to its importance, the Youth series is divided into related sub-series: Events, Advocacy, Adminstrative, and Programs. The majority of the series is housed in electronic records.
  - Events, 8
    Contains files documenting the organization and implementation of events sponsored or attended by the Youth Program division of El Pueblo, Inc. Includes conferences, ceremonies, and presentations.
    - El Foro Juvenil binder, 2010 (Box 20)
    - Enlaces Juveniles conference, 2011; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Youth Organizing Institute binder, 2013 (Box 20)
    - Youth events electronic records, 2006-2015; 671 files in 109 folders; approximately 1 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0004)
  - Advocacy, 9
    The Advocacy sub-series is related to advocacy related to the DREAM act, first introduce in the US Senate in 2001. It showcase drawings and personal stories of children and adolescents affected by legal status.
    - Dream Act children's drawings, 2000s (Box 20)
    - Dream Act dream applications, mid 2000s-early 2010s; 4 folders (Box 20)
  - Administrative, 10
    The Administrative sub-series includes files related to planning, funding, and operation of the youth division. It includes educational material, grant documentation, and other administrative files.
    - Educational manuals, circa early 2000s (Box 20)
    - NC Health and Wellness Trust Fund Commission (HWTF), 2001, 2010-2011; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Z Smith Reynolds Foundation Grant, 2006 (Box 20)
    - Grant for No Fumo, 2008-2009 (Box 20)
    - IPAS Grant, 2010 (Box 20)
    - Derechos Sin Fronteras reproductive rights program, 2012 (Box 20)
    - NC Public Health Grant for teen pregnancy prevention, 2015 (Box 20)
    - Teen pregnancy prevention budget, 2015 (Box 20)
    - Peer educator contracts, 2014-2016; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Youth administrative electronic records, 2001-2015; 1367 files in 226 folders; approximately 1.15 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0003)
      Extensive files related to the administration of the Youth Program division and the Youth Council. Includes strategic planning, media engagement, resources, website development, outreach, and finances. Documents also include grant applications, staffing and logistics, and collaboration with Americorps.
  - Programs, 11
    The Program sub-series documents the main activities of the youth division, especially its various Latino youth leadership iniatives and programs. It includes the Derechos Sin Fronteras sexual and reproductive rights peer education program, the No Fumo anti-tobacco and youth leadership program, the Pueblo Power social justice and educational leadership program and other educational and youth leadership programs.
    This sub-series would be of interest to researchers of Latino youth, youth and non-profits, the history of the anti-tobacco movement, and leadership intiatives.
    - AGAPE, circa 2000s (Box 20)
    - No Fumo leadership guide binder, circa 2000s; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Wake Youth, 2006 (Box 20)
    - Hola proposal, 2007 (Box 20)
    - Derechos Sin Fronteras sexual and reproductive rights, 2011 (Box 20)
    - Family night workshop evaluations, circa mid 2010s (Box 20)
    - Teen pregnancy prevention peer ed pre and post tests, 2013-2015; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Sex ed curriculum feedback, 2013-2015 (Box 20)
    - Teen pregnancy prevention consent forms, 2015-2016 (Box 20)
    - Sex ed workshop evaluation, circa mid 2010s (Box 20)
    - Teen pregnancy prevention mid-program retreat, circa mid 2010s (Box 20)
    - Peer educator retreat evaluations, circa mid 2010s (Box 20)
    - No Fumo 2004 - 2009 (phases 1-3); No Fumo 2009-2012, 2004-2012; 2,681 files in 422 folders; approximately 2.10 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0002)
      Contains documents related to the administration and implementation of all phases of the No Fumo Program. El Pueblo's No Fumo Youth Leadership Program is an innovative statewide youth leadership program, with a focus on capacity-building and tobacco-use prevention among Latino youth.
    - Youth Programs electronic records, 2010-2015; 4,454 files in 635 folders; approximately 4.19 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0006)
      Extensive files documenting programs organized and sponsored by the Youth Program division of El Pueblo, Inc. Includes coalition and community projects, fellowships, the CAPAZ Initiative, and the Pueblo Power Youth Leadership Program.
  - Photographs, 2004-2015
    - Youth photographs, video, and other media electronic records, 2004-2011; 2,703 files in 39 folders; approximately 10.6 GB
      Primarily photo files with some video files. Photos document staff and participants at events attended, organized, and/or sponsored by the Youth Program division of El Pueblo, Inc.
    - Youth photographs, video, and other media electronic records, 2004-2015; 3,845 files in 77 folders; approximately 40.3 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0007)